{
  "reference_number": "2534",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We have the means to be able to implement this and also to regulate this in our own backyard."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Revision usually means pushing forward of targets. We need to make hard line targets and aim for meeting them."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "A three year cycle would be more preferable and also be taken into account when promoting to voters who care about this, to show\n how the change is being met. Yes it's risky, but also it's an excellent deadline to have related to real world situations."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "If another Govt gets in then they could reduce all the funds therefore making it unable to be achieved. A realistic budget including\n contingencies needs to be implemented and continued."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only if it involves putting more money in, because things need to change faster, or there is an initiative that needs backing. However\nit's best to allow for these contingencies at the start."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Plans are steps towards goals. Without these then it's just pie in the sky material. Also plans are deadlines by which we can focus and\nchange tack if necessary."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Work with the people already in these areas. For example, work with the irrigation companies and the regional councils to help\n\nimplement the regulation changes and make them happen, enforcing the rules and penalties and put someone in place to be able to\ndo this. Resources and staffing are a problem, so therefore make them not a problem. The dairy industry are saying \"we need\n\neducation\" when they've already had a lot of education. So therefore, put in place a six month education time limit, go hard on the\neducation so this is not an excuse any more, and then work with the irrigation companies, putting someone on the ground level to\n\nmake sure the regulations are being met. Give them a drone so they can look at the waterways and then they can work together with\nthe irrigation companies to restrict water when the regulations aren't being met. this isn't rocket science. Place a regulation on\nforestry so that they chip the large logs that they are currently leaving on the land (and causing havoc when flooding happens, which\n\nis happening more and more now) and then ship the wood chips out to the farmers to help remidify the soil. Put people at ground\nlevel with the technology to be able to aid the transition and implement the penalties when the regulations aren't met, with strict\n\ndeadlines as to when these need to be met. We've known we need to change for over ten years now, reward those who have been\ntrying to change and penalise those who are stalling. Also look at harsh penalties for Regional Councils that aren't strategising as to\n\nhow we can clean up our act. Put people at ground level monitoring streams and air for pollution and give them the means to\npenalise, making the penalties pay for the wages, this recoups costs."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If the people are from a wide base and NOT lining their pockets with corruption."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Both, but they also need to have someone making sure they have clout, and are making wise decisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Help those already implementing change, work with them, work within the community so that this comes from the bottom up as well\n\nas top down."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I'm happy to be contacted about any of this. Currently I've had many discussions with the Environmental Manager for the Otago\n\nregion irrigation company about how things can change, one of these changes is going to the board now. I am also on a Resiliant\nCommunity Board. We can set President's cases that show how things can change. We can learn from other's. We can learn from our\n\ncommunity and I think it's essential that we work within our community and support our community so we are all collaborating\ntowards the same cause and supporting each other within this and towards better solutions. The comments about the irrigation\n\ncompany are currently being put to the board, so please hold them confidential as they may currently be sensitive information.\nHowever I do think translucency aids support so perhaps soon in the future this information can be released and if it sets a\npresidents case, in fact, promoted. But that time is not right now. If you contact me I can keep you up to date with this as if it\n\nbecomes a president's case I believe it needs as much support and media and publicity as possible, both to show the way we are\nworking together for a better future and to align with the industries to create a not just sustainable future, but one where we are\n\nactually fixing what we've damaged in the past. (e.g. our waterways, which is not just health, but respect to Iwi, Culture, Health,\nEnvironment.... many elements.) We can be a leader with respect to changing things for the better. We have the \"kiwi\" mentality of\n\nmaking things happen and being innovative. Let's work together to make this Country 100% Pure again!"
    }
  ]
}
